Hi, my name's you
...gupta rpm in the windows organization for wi-fi and I'm here with
visual...three and we're going to spend some time talking to
you today about wi-fi direct and wi-fi direct services in windows stand.
Today we'll spend some time talking about what is wi-fi direct and wi-fi direct
services what can you do with this technology with these api what can you build
worker some of the very interesting scenarios...talk about what's new in windows
...then we'll walk through a demo will show you how all of this comes together
after that visuals going to walk you through how simple it...it is to write this code
and then we'll give you a couple of tips on debugging.
In today's world most applications connect to the internet and provide a service to the
users such as facebook or yelp however there is a...of apps
...devices that can benefit from direct connectivity wi-fi direct and services is a
technology that provides this...direct connectivity it allows for
pc's phones are other devices running windows to connect to other
pc's phones or devices the unique value here is
that the devices do not need to be connected to the same access point or even to
...network they can just talk directly with each other once
you are connected once these devices are connected you have a very high-bandwidth
a pipe available to you so you can pump a lot of data you
could move videos you could sink a pc and of phone.
And, it's not just
limited to devices we talked peer-to-peer but you could connect one device to many devices.
Some of the interesting things that are built on this
technology are things like games so let's say you wanted to build a chess
application that two people could use in a park they need to be able
to find each other they need to be able to connect to each other these some very interesting things that start
...and up when you have connectivity directly between two devices you could think about
application such as.
Pc's...phones connecting to devices to control them so
you have a printer you bring it out
...that printer you could do that over wi-fi direct a you could think about long
tail devices such as a quadrant...or you want to be able to communicate with this you want to be able to send and
receive messages from it and you want a long-range the range that comes with wi-fi you
could do this using wi-fi direct and services before we start getting into the details
I wanted to explain the difference between wi-fi direct and wi-fi direct services both
of these technologies are industry standards you could use this technologies to talk between
of windows device another windows device or you could
...use these technologies to talk between windows and any other device that
you're building wi-fi direct came first it allows you to find another device
bear with it connect to it and communicate what wi-fi direct services
ads is an additional layer on top of it so you can actually find the service running on the
more device, for example,
if you were writing a game application you would from a pc find
another pc and that's not very valuable because the pc may or may not be running the game with
wi-fi direct services you could actually find other people who are playing the same game in the
city so you could connect and communicate with them let's talk about
windows ten the api and what's new the first big change
from windows eight-point...to windows stand is that we've added
wi-fi direct services this concept did not exist in windows eight-point one this is a new
emerging technology so we thought it was prudent to added to windows stand.
The second thing is we have significantly, significantly enhance the api
set for wi-fi direct and this is based on feedback that we get from isv,
you know, things that they want to build things that they want to different how it would help them complete
their scenarios so, let's talk about the api in windows
...which is in sharp contrast from eight-point
one the apps have complete control over the experience so the
...can go and find device the app can go...with the device
and pairings important because we use a shared mediums or trust needs to be...the app can
going connect the app can communicate with the device and, you know,
what if you're already getting
bored all of these are concepts that do not need to be exposed to the user
...eight-point one you had to use are user interface to go and find the device
and then use your application and now you can completely do this from
within your application the second thing that we've added as an enhancement
...update to the api is bidirectional control
...one when you use wi-fi direct you always have to find from windows you could
find other devices from windows but you...find windows from other devices we had one directional
support with windows time you can write
an application that says go find me other devices...you can go into a
...that says hey let other people find me let other people find me as a device
let other people find me as a service and to get into a little bit more details of how powerful
this api is applications consent custom information elementsand,
they can read and write these elements if you're familiar with wi-fi
you would know that information elements is a standard extensibility mechanism so let's say
I was building an application for device and, you know,
I can find the device the standard allows for me to know the name of the device
in the serial number but in my application I wanted to show the color of the device the
device...information element that can be read by the application that
knows the color so you could have better experience for the user you can read and write these
information elements we've also talked a lot about what happens to all those devices
are there that want direct connectivity but do not have wi-fi direct
support we've added a mode so that windows can come up as a legacy ap
or standard ap and what would happen when you go into that
node is any device that has wi-fi could connect to windows just as
a network we've also added low-level control and this is again something that you would be
familiar with if you're familiar with wi-fi direct but geo intent is a
very low-level concept in wi-fi direct and are new api
is powerful enough to let the application specify these parameters but,
you know, what enough with the docking let's get into demo and see what all of this looks
like what we're going to show,
you know, we've decided to show a swiss life application this applications going to show you all
the different parameters that you can move edit using your application you don't need to use all of
them what we want to demonstrate is what all is available to you ve
...be going...each one of them what we'll do is we'll go through a demo of wi-fi direct
and then wi-fi direct services and show you how services is different than direct
so let's get to the demo and were handed over...was going to talk a little bit about the api and
then show the demo why phonetic api has to entities with differing
roles and that called as the advertiser and the connector
the advertiser advertises itself over wifi and the connector discovers advertiser and
connects to it for this demo purposes my pc's going to be the advertiser and
...discover my pc and connect to it so let's go ahead and start...advertiser
to start...advertiser we need to turn on the listen state of the pc let's go ahead and do that?
We then start the advertisers.
At this point my pc's discoverable and other pc's can find it and connect to it so
...thought why don't you discover my pc and connect to it let me go here and click
on get devices which calls into the api to find other devices.
All look I...shows pc there should I go...try to connect two-x short.
...that pc and let me hit connect
and windows is asking me if this is okay let's I'm going to say yes.
And, I...connection requests from your cup I'm going-to go ahead and accept is requests.
Windows is now asking me if it's okay to accept this request I'm going to say yes.
...connected so what we just showed you is a direct connection between these two
not you could do this between a pc and of phone you could do this between a pc...
any other device these devices are not on the same network in fact they're
not even connected to any network so going back to our park scenario where, you know,
you...jess application you could find
another bc in you could connect to it and you could start playing chess you do not need to
show all these technical aspect in your application this is to illustrate, you know,
the diversity of the api is that we offer why...send-me some data let's see how
...exchange looks.
And, we're transferring some data between both these pc's.
Next what we're going to show you is wi-fi direct services it's going to
look very similar and will articulate the differences in there?
So, I'm going to disconnect this closer device.
For this we want to do it again...was locate writing...okay.
So, let's go...one more we have...does this is...
What we're going to show you now is wi-fi direct services in
the previous demo one pc found other pc but with wi-fi
direct services you can actually find a service running on the pc so we
show where'd you go ahead and let's create a...service on your pc?
And, is that advertising itself now so by pc's advertising the build two
...fifteen service and...available for other seekers
...and connect to it so you thought why don't you discover my service and connect
to it so I'm going to go and look for the
...twenty fifteen service and if you
...building applications both your applications would already
know the service that they were trying to find each other so the user doesn't need to type in all of this is something that
...application can do so should I had get service...
And, finding services.
And, look,
I found somebody else...this service...to select this...connect.
I see a connection notification from...I'm going-to go ahead and accept...requests.
And,...reconnected now we are connected over
...services...click checked this session.
how do I send some data between...of...so you need to basically ad udp port?
Okay, so, you do that by a socializing random port number here.
And, then just clicking on the tcp button here.
At this point we are connected to what I'll forward and we can proceed with the sending data to each other.
And, conceded...flowing both between both these...again the big difference here,
you know, these demos looks similar but the big difference here is are you trying to find
a device are you trying to find a service running on the device if you
were building games you want to find a service running on the other device because you want to know who
else is playing that game...the game lobby if you're trying to find just
a tv or...phone or something you would use wi-fi direct so let's talk about the
core that power's these...show if you could walk us through what it takes to build
one of these applications short so from the demo app we saw that
...direct api had to distinct roles...advertiser and the connector
...connected to the advertiser let's take a look at how to write the advertisers to start
...advertiser we instantiate an object of the
...direct advertisement publisher class.
The next thing that we do is return on the listen state for the advertiser we said that by setting
the listen state discovery ability property proceeding we enabled advertiser to
accept incoming connection requests from the connector we do that by instantiating
an object of the...direct connection listener class we assign...call back to the connection
...event handler so...a connector...to connect to the advertise at this
...is fired we'll take a look at the connection handler even code in the
next few slides.
The finals step in starting the advertiser is to call the start method on the
publisher that's it at this point but advertiser is advertising
or wi-fi and is ready to accept incoming connection requests from the
connector so what you're saying is if I wanted to make my pc
discoverable it's as simple as you're doing these for steps
correct all right let's talk to these guys about what happens next?
Let's take a look at the connector...
So, this is the other sign this was my pc which was trying to
...your be correct to connect to the advertise that we need to find
advertiser first this can be done by creating a query string for finding why
for direct devices this query string can be
created by calling the get device selector method on the wi-fi direct device object.
This query string.
Also called as a device select that is then pass to the finally
...method on the device information class.
The finalizing method returns
...device information collection object which contains device information objects
which represent...devices found nearby the connector
than proceeds by selecting the desired...device and connect
to connecting to it by calling the from id...method on the...direct device object.
The from id asic method also takes
and optional connection parameters object on which certain connection properties like
...intents can be set.
The from ideas thing method returns to a...
direct device object which represents a connection to your advertiser finally the connector can
proceed in obtaining the remote and local ip addresses by calling the get connection endpoint
...method on this wi-fi direct device objects which
these ip addresses the connector can then
establishes socket connection with the advertiser so on one
side we started been discoverable on the other side we found
the device and tried to connect to it is there some more code on the first sign that
...except the incoming connection yes the next slide I'm going to talk about that.
So, remember that we had said
...call back handler on the advertiser for...thing incoming
connection requests from the connect let's take a look at how the code looks.
So,...the connector tries to connect to the advertiser the connection requested even-handed
...fired the advertiser can then retrieved disconnection
request by calling the get connection request method on the requested event arcs
the advertiser at this point can either choose to accept or reject the request.
For this demo purposes we're going to accept the requests the advertiser can then called the from
...segment on the...for direct device plus.
And, parsing the device information id obtained from this connection requests.
The successful completion of this...returns you...direct device object that represents
...direct device connection to the connector the advertiser can then opt in
ip addresses and proceed with the socket connection at this point both the
advertiser and the connector
...a socket and begin communication all right so that was wi-fi direct and,
you know, what if it sounds like we rush through that...did not get it we're going to
share the full source code of the sample that we demonstrated here so you can start playing with it and building it
into your own application but let's quickly also walk to wi-fi direct services, you know,
we showed to demos wi-fi direct and wi-fi direct services that's what to wi-fi direct services...
So, similar to the lifer direct api concept the...services hasn't advertise
...publishes...service over wifi and the...basically discovers this service and
connects to it let's take a look at what it takes to start...to start...
we instantiate an object of the why phonetics service advertiser class we...in the
service name as a parameter to this classes constructor next we assign a
call back to the session requested even turn that on the advertiser which gets fired whenever a
secret tries to connect to your service the final step in publishing...service is to
call start on the advertiser that's it you now have a service ready for excepting incoming
connection requests from other seekers so if I was writing a game this is what I would
do in the game lobby like if I'm waiting for other people I want them to know that
my game is running instead of the service name like ever
fill that variable up with the content also dot game and everybody else running
the game confinement correct let's take a look at what it takes to start a secret.
To connect to a service the service needs to be discovered for us
to discover service we need to create a query string with that particular service
...that can be done by calling the get selector method on the y
...service class and passing in the service...this query string also called as
a service selector and then be...to the fight finally
...method on the device information class the finalizing method would return
...device information collection object that represents a nearby services
...the...can then proceed to connect to the desired
service by calling the from id asic method on the y fed-ex service class so the
big difference between wi-fi direct and wi-fi direction services is I
would only find people who have the service running correct so the from id
...method on successful completion returns
...fed-ex service class that represents is wi-fi direct service the
...can then proceed to connect to the service by calling the connect basing method
on this object on the successful completion of this method you get a
...service session object that represents a connection to the service the
...can then obtain the local and
...remote ip endpoints from this object and proceed with socket connection.
Let's take a look at what it takes
to accept incoming connection requests from other seekers so we had assigned
...call back to the session requested event handler on the advertiser this call
...gets fired when I want to sequel tries to connect to it to your service.
...can obtain the session request by calling the...session request method on
...requested event arcs the advertiser can then connect to this
...by calling connect
facing and passing in the device information object obtained from the session request.
This method returns you...service session object that represents a connection to the
...can then proceeding obtaining...ip addresses and connecting
over a socket to the...so if we had to summarize both of these
api right you have to basic rules for
the fundamental thing is you have one-sided trying to be discoverable the other
...other site trying to find it you make yourself discoverable and then you wait for incoming
connections that's one role and the other role is you find people who are already discoverable
and connect to it and what we have demonstrated is both sides of the role if you
were working with one windows pc and something else you only need to
implement one side of this roleso, we walked through the code let's talk about,
you know, as people start building these applications water some interesting pips
...tricks that people could follow there are two things that we would advice the first one
windows works under diversity of pc's they work on or pc's they work on new pc's the
...pc's with hardware that has
...wi-fi and others that don't so the first thing that you want to do before you
start building applications you want to make sure that your pc actually supports this capability and
...stand we've added a combined I'm not going to read the whole thing but you can run that command
on your pc and you can see if wi-fi direct and services are
supported you'd see and output like we show here the second thing if you're going to
be working with devices and if you're not able to get connections through or of their failing
of wireless sniffers your best friend...wireless new for shows you what goes on
over-the-air so, you know, packets coming out of this pc how do they look over-the-air and how
to go to the other pc so let's look at what a sniper capture shows
here what you can see here is a wi-fi direct connection it shows you a pc
trying-to connect and bandwidth another pc we're going to include a sample capture
with this presentation so you can download that and you can...you can look at what a successful connection looks
like and play with it this messages that you see over here they're all very
valid defined in the industry-standard so-if you have questions
about the messages I would recommend you start reading the industry-standard?
So, let's recap about what...spoken about today wi-fi direct
and services industry standards that allows interoperability between windows and
non windows devices these api is that allow you to
created direct connection without needing connectivity to an ap or to the internet
v think that some of the most interesting use cases of games
and applications that allow you to...devices, you know,
and, utilities things such as file sharing these are things that we have
come up with we'd really like to understand what you are going to build.
If you need information about the standards not about the
api is if you need information about the standards their available from wi-fi
lines and all information about this api and these samples they're going to be published here
soon on msdn we'd like to thank you for listening to us and hope you enjoyed representation
we look forward to senior apps...a app store thank you thank you.